He was released?
Wypuszczono go?
Yes. Johan Liebert was released this morning.
Tak, Johan Liebert wyszedł dziś rano.
Oh, I see.
Rozumiem.
I heard he suddenly fainted, but I guess it was not serious.
Powiedziano mi, że zemdlał, ale widać nie było to nic poważnego.
Oh…
Och…
I see you at the library a lot.
Często panią widuję w bibliotece.
Aren't you a librarian at the university library?
Jest pani bibliotekarką na uczelni?
Is that right? He was released, was he?
Naprawdę? Wypuszczono go?
I'm glad to hear it. I was so worried when it happened.
Miło słyszeć. Zmartwiłam się, gdy zasłabł.
He faint right in front of you?
Zemdlał przy pani?
Yes. He was looking for a book and I was helping him.
Tak, szukał książki, a ja mu doradzałam.
Then he suddenly fainted?
I nagle zasłabł?
That's right. But first, he screamed.
Tak, choć najpierw krzyknął.
He did?
Naprawdę?
He was looking at a picture book, and when he turned the page, he screamed.
Oglądał książkę z obrazkami, przewrócił stronę i krzyknął.
A picture book?
Książkę z obrazkami?
At the Edge of Darkness
ROZDZIAŁ 34 NA SKRAJU MROKU
Your EEG results were normal though, so your brain is fine.
Twoje wyniki EEG były w normie, więc mózg ma się dobrze.
You're in perfect health.
Jesteś w pełni zdrowy.
The doctor thinks it was caused by anemia or fatigue.
Lekarz podejrzewa anemię lub wycieńczenie.
If not, then he said you must have experienced some kind of incredible shock.
Ewentualnie stawia na mocny szok.
By the way, I didn't know you have a surgery scar on your head.
Swoją drogą nie wiedziałem, że masz bliznę pooperacyjną na głowie.
At any rate, take a break from work and school and take it easy for a while.
Tak czy inaczej przyda ci się przerwa od pracy i szkoły.
Oh, that reminds me.
No właśnie.
A letter arrived for you while you were in the hospital.
Przyszedł do ciebie list, gdy leżałeś w szpitalu.
A letter?
List?
It doesn't have a return address.
Nie ma adresu zwrotnego.
I doubt it is a letter bomb though.
Raczej nie ma bomby w środku.
What is it? What's so funny?
O co chodzi? Co cię tak bawi?
Who's it from?
Od kogo jest ten list?
The Red Hindenburg.
Od Czerwonej Hindenburg.
What?
Co?
You look awfully wholesome to be wandering around here.
Co tu robi ktoś z taką prezencją?
You must be lost. Or maybe you are here to pop your cherry.
Zgubiłeś się? A może chcesz stracić cnotę?
I'll be gentle with you and teach you the ropes. Come with me.
Będę delikatna i wprowadzę cię w temat. Chodź.
Have you heard of the Red Hindenburg?
Słyszała pani o Czerwonej Hindenburg?
What?
Co?
It says the Red Hindenburg is around here.
Napisano tu, że w tej okolicy znajdę Czerwoną Hinderburg.
What? At your age?
Co? W twoim wieku?
I see you've already got some pretty damn weird fetishes.
Już masz różne dziwne fetysze?
She's down there.
Szukaj jej tam.
I need a fix. Give me something.
Potrzebuję działkę. Daj mi coś.
Is the Red Hindenburg up these stairs?
Czy Czerwona Hinderburg jest na górze?
Come in.
Proszę wejść.
I'm glad you came.
Miło, że przybyłeś.
Have a seat right there.
Usiądź tam.
Ah yes, there's that face of yours.
Ach ta twoja buźka.
Such good looks.
Taki przystojniaczek.
I saw you with Schuwald on the TV news.
Zobaczyłam cię z Schuwaldem w wiadomościach.
So now you're the Red Hindenburg after pretending to be Margot Langer?
Teraz jesteś Czerwoną Hindenburg i już nie udajesz Margot Langer?
And before that, I was Blue Sophie.
A wcześniej byłam Niebieską Sophie.
Names don't mean anything anyway.
Imiona nie mają znaczenia.
Isn't that right, Johan Liebert?
Prawda, Johanie Liebert?
At any rate, it's the name my boyfriend calls me.
W każdym razie tak mnie nazywa mój chłopak.
He's right behind that door.
Stoi za tymi drzwiami.
Isn't that right, honey?
Prawda, skarbie?
So don't try anything funny.
Więc nie próbuj niczego.
He's got a big gun cocked and ready behind that door.
Za tymi drzwiami trzyma dużą, naładowaną broń.
The one in his pants is pretty big too.
Ta w spodniach też jest niczego sobie.
I was impressed.
Byłam pod wrażeniem.
That must be a hell of a scheme you worked out
Musiałeś wykombinować niezły plan,
to cozy up to that fat cat Schuwald.
że wszedłeś w łaski tego krezusa, Schuwalda.
That was pretty impressive.
Robi to wrażenie.
I remember when you brought that young guy Fahren to me.
Pamiętam, kiedy przyprowadziłeś tego młodego Fahrena.
Who would've thought Schuwald's actual son would show up later?
Kto by pomyślał, że zjawi się prawdziwy syn Schuwalda?
That poor Fahren guy.
Biedny Fahren.
Once you were done with him, you had him kill himself.
Kiedy z nim skończyłeś, skłoniłeś go do samobójstwa.
It's taken me a whole two years.
Zajęło mi to dwa lata.
You see, it was two years ago that the real Margot Langer opportunely died.
Los tak chciał,
When she died,
Po jej śmierci
I was able to reap the benefits of using her name.
używałam jej imienia, co dawało pewne korzyści.
But it wasn't like I was close to her.
Ale nie byłyśmy ze sobą blisko.
She wasn't a whore anymore. She had gotten out of the business.
Przestała być dziwką, odeszła z biznesu.
All I had to do was loosen her up with a few drinks.
Wystarczyło rozluźnić ją kilkoma drinkami.
She probably had no one to speak to for years.
Pewnie od lat nie miała z kim rozmawiać.
Once she was drunk, a few crocodile tears from me and she blabbed everything.
Trochę moich krokodylich łez, alkoholu i wszystko mi wygadała.
All about her romance with Schuwald and her son she gave up for adoption.
O romansie z Schuwaldem i synem oddanym do adopcji.
Then the woman got herself killed.
Potem kobieta dała się zabić,
that let me pretend to be Margot Langer and squeeze a bundle out of Schuwald.
więc mogłam udawać Margot Langer i wycisnąć od Schuwalda małą fortunę.
The police concluded that she was murdered by a random attacker.
Policja stwierdziła, że zamordował ją przypadkowy zbir.
I bet they never had a clue she was just a small part of a huge scheme.
Założę się, że nie mieli pojęcia,
Oh, that's right.
No tak.
And then there's what happened to that poor detective Richard.
A tego detektywa Richarda spotkał tak przykry los.
If only he hadn't stuck his nose in things,
Gdyby nie wściubiał wszędzie nosa, nie skończyłby tak marnie.
So, what's the body count now?
To ile już masz trupów na swoim koncie?
All right, that's enough pleasant reminiscing.
Racja. Już dość tych miłych wspominek.
It's time to get down to business.
Przejdę do rzeczy.
And don't even think about trying to squirm your way out of it.
Nie próbuj się nawet z tego wywinąć.
Isn't that right, honey?
Prawda, skarbie?
Come on, make me an offer.
Dalej, złóż mi ofertę!
Are you deaf?
Ogłuchłeś?
What do you think is the ultimate fear?
Jak myślisz, czym jest największy strach?
What?
Co?
I thought I'd already reached the depths of the darkness.
Myślałem, że już sięgnąłem najgłębszych czeluści mroku.
Don't try to change the subject.
Nie próbuj zmieniać tematu.
But now I've seen…
Ale teraz widzę…
even deeper darkness beyond it.
że głębiej czyha jeszcze większa ciemność.
What?
Co?
Stop right there!
Stój! Myślisz, że możesz sobie po prostu odejść?
I'm through with this.
Kończę z tym.
I'm not interested in Schuwald anymore.
Nie interesuje mnie już Schuwald.
Don't screw around with me!
Nie pogrywaj ze mną!
It's useless.
To na nic.
You see, I don't even exist.
Bo ja nawet nie istnieję.
I've had it with your crap!
Mam dość tych twoich bzdur!
Honey! Get out here now!
Skarbie! Chodź tu!
Honey! What are you doing? Roberto!
Skarbie, co ty robisz? Roberto?
May I have one of your balloons?
Mogę prosić o jeden z twoich balonów?
Use this to get your fix.
Wydaj to na swoją działkę.
CARSTENSEN STREET (MUNICH)
ULICA CARSTENSENA (MONACHIUM)
Doctor! When is it our turn? He's bleeding from his head!
Doktorze, kiedy nasza kolej? Krwawi z głowy.
-Screw you! My kid's first! -It hurts!
- Wal się! Najpierw moje dzieci. - Boli!
-Quit whining! It is just a broken arm!
- Nie zrzędź! To tylko złamana ręka!
Cut out the racket and wait for your darn turn!
Dość tego hałasu i czekaj na swoją cholerną kolej.
Crying won't help anyone anyway. There's only one great doctor here.
Płacz nic nie pomoże. Jest tu tylko jeden świetny lekarz.
What's with that long stick thing you are carrying?
Co to za długi kij?
It's nothing.
Nic takiego.
Say, is the doctor here really that great?
Ten lekarz naprawdę jest taki wybitny?
You better believe it. Without this doctor, all the Asians around here
Żebyś wiedział. Bez niego wszyscy Azjaci,
especially the Vietnamese, would be dead.
a zwłaszcza Wietnamczycy, byliby już martwi.
Is that right?
Naprawdę?
You're not Vietnamese, are you?
Nie jesteś Wietnamczykiem, co?
No, I'm not.
Nie.
Hey, wait your turn!
Czekaj na swoją kolej!
You look pretty pale, but the injured go first.
Wyglądasz blado, ale ranni mają pierwszeństwo.
I'm not a patient.
Nie jestem pacjentem.
Hey, sit down and wait your turn.
Siadaj i czekaj na swoją kolej.
Hurry up and see my pal, doc!
Szybko, zobacz mojego kolegę, doktorku!
My kid's first!
Najpierw moje dziecko!
-Excuse me. -Hey, what's your problem?
- Przepraszam. - A tobie co?
Wait your turn, dammit!
Cholera, czekaj na swoją kolej!
Excuse me, doctor. There's something I would like to ask you.
Przepraszam, doktorze. Chciałbym o coś zapytać.
Quit making me repeat myself! Wait outside!
Nie każcie mi się powtarzać! Czekajcie na zewnątrz!
I don't have time for you now.
Nie mam dla pana czasu.
A woman and what's more…
Kobieta i do tego…
Didn't you hear me? Get out.
Nie słyszy pan? Proszę wyjść.
She looks so young.
Wydaje się bardzo młoda.
I'm suturing now. Don't interfere.
Robię szwy. Proszę nie przeszkadzać.
If anything happens to him, it'll be your fault.
Jeśli coś mu się stanie, pan za to odpowie.
Looks like a stab wound to the thigh. Must be from a knife.
Rana kłuta w udo. Pewnie nóż.
Her suturing is very neat.
Bardzo sprawne szwy.
However…
Jednakże…
You should insert a drainage tube.
Powinna pani założyć dren.
Why don't you just butt out?
Może się pan odczepić?
If you don't, then you need to get him to a proper hospital right away.
Inaczej trzeba będzie zawieźć go do normalnego szpitala.
A proper hospital?
Normalnego szpitala?
-This is a proper-- -It's no hospital.
- To jest… - To nie jest szpital.
Just from looking at you, I can tell you're not a real doctor.
Przecież widzę, że nie jest pani prawdziwym lekarzem.
If I could take him to a proper hospital, I already would have.
Gdybym mogła, zabrałabym go już do zwykłego szpitala.
Most of the people here are undocumented or illegal immigrants.
Większość osób to nieudokumentowani albo nielegalni imigranci.
If they went to a real hospital, they'd be seized right away
W prawdziwym szpitalu od razu by ich zgarnięto
and sent back to their country.
i odesłano do kraju.
How many of them
Jak pan myśli,
do you think have died because they couldn't go to a proper hospital?
ilu z nich zmarło, bo nie mogli pójść do szpitala?
Don't preach about things you are ignorant of.
Bez kazań, jeśli się pan nie zna.
Put in a drainage tube.
Proszę założyć mu dren.
The knife he was stabbed with was probably dirty.
Nóż, którym go dźgnięto, był zapewne brudny.
Right.
- Dobrze. - Zdejmie pani jeden lub dwa szwy.
Okay.
Dobrze.
Insert the drainage tube about five centimeters in.
Rurkę drenażową wsunąć na około pięć centymetrów.
Good. Well done.
Dobra robota.
Thanks.
Dziękuję.
Who's next?
Kto następny?
You awake?
Jest pani przytomna?
The patients told me you've been working for 48 hours straight without rest.
Pacjenci mówili, że pracowała pani bez przerwy od 48 godzin.
I checked on the other patients you'd already treated.
Sprawdziłem pacjentów, których już pani leczyła.
You're pretty darn good for an underground doctor.
Cholernie dobrze jak na podziemną lekarkę.
How old are you?
Ile ma pani lat?
Seventeen.
Siedemnaście.
You're kidding! You're so young,
Żartuje pani! Taka młoda,
but you're practically like a real GP.
a ma pani wiedzę niczym lekarz rodzinny.
I just happened to be here
Po prostu tu byłam,
when the doctor that used to run it disappeared and left all his equipment.
gdy lekarz, który to prowadził, zniknął i zostawił cały sprzęt.
Having the equipment doesn't make you a doctor.
Sprzęt to za mało, żeby zostać lekarzem.
Where'd you learn what you know?
Gdzie się pani tego nauczyła?
My father used to be a doctor.
Mój tata był lekarzem.
"Used to?"
Był?
He was a doctor in Vietnam
Tak, w Wietnamie.
and brought me with him when he came to study in East Germany.
Przyjechałam tu z nim, gdy zaczął studia w NRD.
He stayed on here and opened a small clinic.
Został tu i otworzył małą klinikę.
But when the wall came down,
Kiedy runął mur,
he kept doing what he could to help the people who would come here from Asia.
robił, co mógł, żeby pomóc imigrantom z Azji.
But then…
Ale wtedy…
some neo-Nazi punk killed my father.
jakiś drań neonazista zabił mojego ojca.
He was killed just because his skin was a different color.
Zginął, bo miał inny kolor skóry.
I was all on my own then and was sent to foster care.
Zostałam sama i trafiłam do opieki zastępczej.
Then a German family adopted me.
Adoptowała mnie niemiecka rodzina.
But they only took me in so they'd look like good Samaritans.
Zrobili to tylko po to, żeby wyjść na dobrych samarytan.
"Look how we saved this poor yellow-skinned girl."
„Uratowaliśmy to biedactwo z żółtą skórą”.
Ever since I was little, I would help my father.
Pomagałam ojcu, odkąd byłam mała.
I read a lot of the medical books he left behind too.
Czytałam też książki medyczne, które zostawił po sobie.
I made up my mind to carry on the work my father was doing.
Postanowiłam kontynuować pracę ojca.
Step aside. I'll finish up here.
Proszę się odsunąć. Skończę to.
There you go. Take it easy until it heals, all right?
Proszę. Oszczędzaj rękę, dopóki się nie zagoi.
Okay.
Dobra.
Okay, next patient.
Następny pacjent.
I took care of everyone.
Zająłem się wszystkimi.
You should go back and study to become a proper doctor.
Powinnaś zacząć studia lekarskie.
People who study hard in this country can find opportunities.
W tym kraju tylko ciężką nauką można dorobić się kariery.
I can see that you are a real doctor.
Widzę, że jest pan prawdziwym lekarzem.
You just don't want amateurs like me around.
Nie chce pan amatorów przy sobie.
That's not what I mean. All I'm saying--
Nie o to mi chodzi. Mówię tylko…
Without me around, what'll happen to these people?
Co się stanie z tym ludźmi, gdy mnie nie będzie?
Who'll take care of them?
Kto się nimi zajmie?
That's no reason--
To nie powód.…
Mom!
Mamo!
What happened?
Co się stało?
My pimp. He lost his temper… and shot me.
Mój alfons. Wkurzył się i mnie postrzelił.
Mom!
Mamo!
Did she walk all the way here even after being shot?
Szła tu całą drogę po postrzale?
Mom said you could fix her up!
Mama mówiła, że może ją pani wyleczyć!
-You're kidding! -Save her! Please, save my mom!
- To niepoważne! - Uratuj ją! Proszę, uratuj moją mamę.
Okay. It'll be all right. Leave this to me.
Będzie dobrze. Zostaw to mnie.
Please, doctor!
Proszę, pani doktor!
-Mom! -She is a street walker.
- Mamo! - Jest prostytutką.
They're always the ones this kind of thing happens to.
To się zawsze przytrafia takim osobom.
I want to do something for her, but this is beyond me.
Chcę jej jakoś pomóc, ale to mnie przerasta.
Put her on the operating table. Grab her legs.
Połóż ją na stole operacyjnym. Złap za nogi.
It's useless! This is one time that we have to go to a real hospital!
To na nic! Ona naprawdę musi jechać do szpitala!
She'll be dead before we get her there!
Umrze, zanim tam dotrzemy.
I don't have the skills for this! There's nothing I can do!
Nie mam takiej wiedzy! Nie dam rady jej pomóc!
Don't ever give up!
Nigdy się nie poddawaj!
As long as your patient breathes, never ever give up hope.
Dopóki pacjent oddycha, nie trać nadziei.
Don't give up hope!
Nie trać nadziei!
If her celiac artery had been damaged,
Gdyby uszkodziło jej pień trzewny,
her BP would have dropped and she'd have gone into shock.
ciśnienie krwi spadłoby i doznałaby wstrząsu.
But if she was able to walk all the way here,
Skoro udało jej się przejść całą drogę,
she's still in pre-shock and her BP is only falling slowly.
nadal jest w stanie szoku i ciśnienie powoli spada.
Judging from the gunshot wound, it's likely her spleen has been damaged.
Sądząc po ranie postrzałowej, uszkodzono jej śledzionę.
In other words, if we perform emergency surgery while infusing blood,
Czyli jeśli wykonamy operację, podając jej krew, wciąż jest nadzieja.
Okay, let us begin.
Zaczynajmy.
Take the scalpel.
Weź skalpel.
He seems to be sleeping soundly.
Smacznie sobie śpi.
Miraculously, there was no damage to bones, intestines,
Jakimś cudem nie uszkodzono kości, jelit
or any other part of her digestive system.
ani reszty układu trawiennego.
She's lucky all we had to do was remove the damaged part of her spleen.
Ma szczęście, że wystarczyło usunąć uszkodzoną część śledziony.
That was magnificent surgery.
Świetna operacja.
Only because you were helping me.
Bo mi pan pomógł.
Mom…
Mamo…
Dr. Tenma.
Doktorze Tenma.
Please work here.
Proszę tu pracować.
I only came here because I had something to ask you.
Przyszedłem tu, bo chciałem panią o coś zapytać.
I saw this newspaper article.
Zobaczyłem ten artykuł.
This is Blue Sophie, aka the Red Hindenburg.
To Niebieska Sophie, znana też jako Czerwona Hinderburg.
I heard you were first on the scene of this prostitute's murder.
Ponoć była pani pierwszą osobą na miejscu morderstwa prostytutki.
Yes, that's right.
Zgadza się.
Can you describe the scene to me?
Może mi pani opisać miejsce zbrodni?
That night, someone from that area called, so I went.
Tamtej nocy zadzwonił ktoś z dzielnicy, więc się tam udałam.
She'd been shot through the head. She died instantly.
Postrzelono ją w głowę. Umarła na miejscu.
I've seen murders like that many times.
Wiele razy widziałam takie morderstwa, ale tam było inaczej.
The feeling I got when I entered that room…
Gdy weszłam do pokoju, poczułam…
It wasn't a robbery or motivated by malice.
że to nie był rabunek czy zbrodnia w afekcie.
She was just killed for the heck of it.
Została zabita dla frajdy.
Johan!
Johan!
Once you're in the darkness, you just sink deeper into it.
Gdy utkniesz w mroku, tylko zagłębiasz się w nim.
Keep your light shining.
Nie przestawaj świecić.
Listen, you study hard. I know you can become a doctor.
Proszę pilnie się uczyć. Jestem pewien, że zostanie pani lekarką.
You'll make a fine doctor for sure.
Byłaby pani w tym wyśmienita.
Wait! Where are you going, Dr. Tenma?
Chwila! Dokąd pan idzie, doktorze Tenma?
To me, it seems like
Mam nieodparte wrażenie,
you're the one who's sinking into the darkness!
że to pan coraz bardziej pogrąża się w mroku.
You'll come back, won't you, Dr. Tenma?
Wróci pan, prawda, doktorze Tenma?
My Nameless Hero
ROZDZIAŁ 35 BEZIMIENNY BOHATER